do we have our sound connected yes we do
we have our image connected yes we do
oh my God I haven't been on here for so
long this is so weird
this is indeed
Yours Truly Professor Johanna Sophia of
Johannes raw foods and coaching and the
Rossum life
project rossumlife global.com
and now also a real estate Adventure
and this is the fitness series
that will go
into particular segments
um for this June Rejuvenation but also
for the app so that's probably where
you're seeing it
so today is the introduction into
fitness over 50. and for those of you
who've already participated a bunch
you'll just get a refresher of why we're
doing certain things and what is
important here
so today is just the introduction even
though I'm going to go through a quick
routine
um
so that you see it all in practice and
do a little bit of everything but this
program
will emphasize each class emphasize a
particular part of our body and why that
is important so let me just go over
the
10 steps
and that is
the introduction
obviously when it's an overview
um we go emphasizing arms as we age you
know especially as women we lose muscle
tissue and especially of course muscle
tissue in the back where we can do
relatively little but still in the
overall we can do a bit to tame those
those sagginesses which you know again
we have to fall in love with our
wrinkles eventually if we want to be
happy so I have long decided I love my
wrinkles as long as my face stays
shapely and it stays shapely because of
running because of exercising and of
course because of enough rest which is
just as important breathing and all of
that good stuff too posture you know if
I just was sitting like this it would
not be as good so
um
and we have to remind ourselves of all
of that all right so the steps in this
program emphasizing although we always
work on the entire body we emphasize
certain areas of the body we start with
arms
we go to back of course so many people
complain about backaches and
um waking up with backaches and whatever
that is called what's that called when
you suddenly have a pain in your back
and then you become all
stiff for a couple of days
um my ex would have those sporadically
and be like crippled but he refused to
do the exercises I showed him even back
then
so um you know obviously many of us also
invite our own pains
aches and pains as we age because we
don't want to do what we know would help
um so then we emphasize the back then we
emphasize the waist and that is the
flexibility of the waist but of course
abdominal muscles are very important to
keep our waist strong waist and small of
the back are particularly important
because as I always emphasize our entire
upper body has nothing but a spine and
that is loose vertebrae on top of each
other to hold us upright everything else
is soft tissues is organs is muscle
tissue that holds the upper body on top
of the lower body right there is no bone
structure on our sides or front that
will hold us up so
strengthening the abdominal muscle
tissue and the entire waist all the way
around is crucial
to allow us to stay upright and not
crumble and
go crooked
now of course there are other reasons
why we have osteoporosis Etc I'll talk
about that another time
has a lot to do with the consumption of
dairy and other animal products
um we think we get calcium from them but
we don't we actually erode our own
calcium and interfere with our calcium
absorption from
plants which is where we should get it
from when we consume those animal
products particularly Dairy and it
enhances
osteoporosis
so
so we're at the midsection the waist
next is of course something that over
the last couple of decades has become so
much more a prominent feature in the
female that is our butt I don't know why
but you know I I laugh at these
ridiculous butt implants and and of
course they don't do diddly other than
destroy the person's immune system
because you have this foreign entity
there
that has no usefulness you know yes I
have foreign entities in my teeth here
that are fake
um but there's usefulness in them it
helps me chew the food so I can get good
food into my body
you know what I mean there's no purpose
to a butt implant
um
and I don't even think it actually
enhances any kind of sexual experience
or
um confidence experience in the long run
it look they always look fake they don't
know butt wobbles like that or just like
ah humans please
stop it so but if we strengthen our butt
muscles our glutes our
behind it helps us significantly in
walking and getting up and running in
all kinds of functions that are crucial
again to being upright and at ease in
uprightness so the particular butt
exercises and I call them buttser sizes
so you'll have fun when we get to the
better sizes I promise
then we work on our thighs and knees
um knees of course being the one joint
that well actually hips of course hips
and butt again go together you know the
butt exercises better sizes will help
your hip joints to remain flexible and
Juiced up and so you don't have to get a
hip replacement
um
problem is you have to do them you have
to do the exercises for your hips to
actually
remain
functioning and not erode and again you
know osteoporosis plays into that as
well same with our knees so the thighs
and knees help us to get up
um there's another level at which we do
get ups but
um
but yeah working on strengthening our
thigh muscles back and front and our
knee muscles
helps us to get up from a chair right
without having to like push on something
or hold on to something
so
thighs and knees
then there is a series of exercises that
I learned from my personal trainer that
I had the luxury of having last summer
it was wonderful
um that are specifically for strength
and endurance and they're quite
wonderful because
they allow us to feel that empowerment
that we get from I never thought I could
stand that long on one leg or on on you
know or matchup Toes or the that kind of
strength exercise
of course strength exercise also help to
balance many of us I'm ahead of
everybody else
lose our balance I've long lost my
proper balance because of too many ear
infections as a child and as a young
woman
again related to Dairy consumption and I
know you're tired of hearing it but it's
the truth
um
so balance is enhanced by those strength
exercises or rather we can better handle
the lack of balance when we have the
muscle strength to keep us or get us
back into position after we lose our
balance
you know as we turn we often lose
balance okay then we have a series of
those get-ups again specifically
focusing on so that's number eight is
get UPS
um getting up from places getting up
from the floor and there are exercises
that strengthen exactly those muscle
tissues so that it becomes easier to get
up without stumbling fumbling and or
calling for help right
um
now I have never fallen yet
um but of course many people as we age
have a tendency to stumble and fall or
turn and lose their balance and fall
um so getting back up is the number one
concern of
um the elderly
of us elderly I'm going to be 17 in a
couple of months so you all have to
celebrate with me
[Music]
so yeah
get UPS then we have number nine
something that many people don't even
realize is part of fitness
and that is breathing breathing
now
um some of my exercises automatically
involve
breathing
because
they are rhythmically
um
repetitive and that enhances a
repetitive breathing pattern
but in many cases we actually can
self-empower
and Infuse our muscle tissue with extra
red blood cells when we know how to use
breathing to encourage circulation and
to encourage relaxation and to encourage
functioning of all parts of our body
it's a beautiful thing some of you may
have heard of Wim Hof
the famous Iceman
he has developed very simple but
incredibly effective breathing patterns
that I love particularly yes more so
than the yoga breathing exercises that I
had learned in the past
because I find them actually simpler and
more effective
but of course you know the Wim hof2
learned breathing all together from some
yoga practicing and from his own
underwater experiences of holding his
breath in cold water underwater
all right and number 10 has to be
rest or rather in this case since we're
not doing an exercise program on
sleeping
yes today's exercise is sleep for eight
hours straight
um but we are learning
to completely relax our body
in seconds
as opposed to
taking hours
so that is a practice that
um The Learning doesn't work in seconds
the learning takes
more like 10 minutes
um but then you get to a point in at
which you are so able to
see when I just did that how my arms are
completely floppy
um now I've practiced this and taught
this for decades I developed the entire
relaxation program that I teach at my
studio in Zimbabwe in 1982 so it goes
back a little bit
foreign
because I developed many methods there
that are not culturally influenced many
methods for movement and practice of
exercise
that are not
coming out of classical dance or coming
out of
um
even in African culture but that are
neutral in a way that can be done in all
cultures we all breathe and we all can
relax
our entire muscle tissue our body so
and then of course 11 and 12.
let's have 12 classes 11 and 12 will be
creating the more personalized programs
that work for you that you love and or
creating the program where you say I
need to challenge X I need to really
challenge my flabby belly and therefore
I need extra work on uh about so it's on
our belly or on I need to really get
this back
at ease so it never happens again when I
bend down that I suddenly have pain in
my back
Etc or in my neck you know whatever it
is so everybody needs to personalize
their programs and challenge themselves
where they need strengthening but also
you know enjoy where they have fun doing
ways doing things their particular way
so
and
um
and 12
can be a sharing of
what other people do just little
Snippets where we can always learn from
each other because I very much believe
that
we
plagiarism is actually learning so when
we learn from everything we do in this
life on this planet is of course learned
from other human beings nobody has
invented the entire culture
and the snap of a finger
so we learn from each other we bring in
other ideas and we configure what works
best for us and of course what works
best for us can also evolve and change
and
mutate like certainly I have gone
through going to kickboxing classes and
aerobics classes and yoga classes and
I've done you know the stair master and
and I realized that all those
modalities are not really me I wanted
something that I can do without machines
without elaborate outfits or
stuff
um and in any space as long as there's a
little bit of space all I all you need
is a little bit of space and a chair
some of my exercises are helped by being
on a chair rather than on the floor
um
and
so we each develop our
program for me it was also very
important that my program can travel
with me wherever I go yes of course if
you stay at hotels there will be a gym
and you can get your StairMaster in any
gym at any hotel but since I often don't
stay at hotels but at people's hell
homes or
um
or yeah
or in a tent or wherever I might be
um I want to be able to do my exercise
program one way or another
all right
so 12 is gathering
and
fertilizing each other's Concepts
Concepts and ideas
all right
um
it's an interesting thing what I'm doing
here sometimes
we plan everything ahead of time
sometimes the best things come to us as
we're in the middle of it so I have just
laid out the fitness program for this
program partially ahead of time and
partially as I'm sitting here
all right we shall do the basic
run through my routine
with very few repetitions because I
don't want to take too much time but
next week we will do
proper amounts of repetition to really
build
okay
the routine is always
that I will
tilt up the camera
and the futon really is in the way there
and turn down this light
so that it'll be in my face
and get going
okay and
put the microphone forward
maybe have a little green smoothie
hmm
so good I don't know that's just nothing
like smoothies
[Music]
okay
so we start with
upright
stretch to make sure our back says
straight our legs are straight
our neck is straight and we reach two
three four we all we operate on the
count of eight
that has to do with
music
for
five
six
seven
h
has to do with music because most music
operates on a four beat
there's some threes that are the waltzes
and other
but a lot of music internationally
operates on a one two three four five
six seven eight one and of course
um
classical dance and modern dance
training has picked that up and we're
used to those rhythms and if you play
any pop songs or so you will notice that
there's this four beat Rhythm classical
music too
for the most part and it'll help you
stay on the beat if you have an eight
count ten counts never apply so there's
never a one two three four five one two
three four five it's not a musical
rhythm
um there are the odd ones that I've four
or five or three five
um
actually I I wrote a song myself that
has a four or five beat in it
foreign
[Music]
no it's not a well
I'll think about it
I wrote it in the 80s with my Zimbabwean
band
very great musicians
and
yeah so there are some also some
indigenous music pieces that have these
Off beats
um but yeah they're rare so we operate
on eight
next is my little ritual
I love you my planet
I love you my sunshine
I love you Humanity
and I love you my body
it's kind of my way of embracing life
and myself in this world
and you know of course the purpose of
Fitness is so that we can function
better in this lifetime on this planet
in this world of humanity right I mean
why else would we do Fitness
okay the first exercise is actually in
the routine not emphasizing arms which
we're doing a little later but is always
softening out
and strengthening at the same time
the back and the midsection
and it is a turn
that is led by the eyes so your eyes
want to go and look as far as you can
your arms dangle and kind of enhance
that turn by Loosely dangling do not do
this
this is not a raw robot turn this is a
elegant
floppy turn
I had this one client who would always
turn like this
and I couldn't get him to relax I think
um his level of fear of losing his
balance was so
so in his muscle tissue that with all
the intellectual understanding he just
couldn't let go and do this it would
always be like
this so that's not what we want to do we
do not want to do robot turns we want to
do sloppy Trends bend your knees a
little bit feel that you're holding onto
the floor with your feet and look as far
as you can behind yourself and over your
other shoulder
and let your arms fling loosely
and what we do about 80 of these turns
five
six
seven eight and one
two
three four
five
six
seven eight number three or a set of set
is number three
always lead with your eyes really turn
it makes it an eye exercise too
and one
two
three
four
five
six
seven eight six
two
three
four
five
six
seven seven
two
three
four
five
six
seven eight
eight
eight three
four
five counting also helps us to keep
going
nine
because otherwise we think oh that's
enough
fix
seven last one ten
three
four
five
six
seven
eight and suddenly we feel that our neck
really needed that loosening up and
um organs get a nice gentle massage all
of it
benefits all of our Body Benefits I'm
trying to create all exercises in such a
manner that the entire body benefits not
just one isolated part
okay
next we would do but we're not doing
much of it today because I want to get
to the weights
burps always have to be let out
especially when you drink smoothies
smoothies contain a lot of water because
they're whipped
so you need to let out that air that
contain a lot of air not water I mean
they could take water too but
a lot of air so the air needs to come
out of your
system
all right next we're going to do the
wave
and that is curl up
and flat down
and curl up
and flat down or chin in and chin up
and Chin in and chin up
yeah yeah yeah
now for those of you who are starting
out that's just going to be a small
movement here
kicking yourself in the back kicking
yourself in the front you know imaginary
and for those who are more advanced it's
all the way down
and pushing with your thighs back up and
letting your back really experience that
soft
okay we typically do
eight slow ones and
eight fast ones
and then we do a back bounce
we bounce
two three four
five with a very flat back holding all
those muscles
that that keep your spine upright right
holding them you can actually feel them
here again chin is up forward
and you're bouncing that back the knees
are also bouncing a little bit and then
we make it harder by putting our hands
in the under the chin and even harder by
putting our arms out to the front
like that
then we go a little bit to this side and
a little bit to that side so all
together we're going to do again
about
40 bounces
and
of course it gets harder the longer
you stay in that position
but that's what strengthens our back
these are the main back exercises the
twist
the wave
and the bounce the back bounce
very very important for strengthening
the small of your back and allowing you
to stand and walk upright
as opposed to
this right
so yeah
um now today because
I'm going to
um
yeah for myself uh go going to the
weights
and I'll show you the weight routine I
will show you the entire weight routine
and then just quickly go through as an
introduction the other moves that we're
doing
um in a shortened version
because this is just the introduction
Ciao Bella
[Music]
bye darling
I'm letting her out right yeah you can
all right
cat is allowed out
um
the positioning again for working with
weights
should be that your knees are slightly
bent
make sure your knees don't fall toward
each other right but they're straight
and
your butt is not sticking out like that
but in and your upright your shoulders
are down
and you're going one
two
and you keep the entire body
flexible
do not stand stiff with weights as we
age you know we don't want to do like
I'm stiff I'm just doing this uh
in my book
the entire body is involved and if you
have to like swing a little bit to get
those weights up there that's fine
all right
um so our routine is and I'm gonna try
and make a short version actually with
just four count where we normally do
eight one
two
three
four
next comes to the outside one
two
three
four
then we go up
to the ceiling one
two
three
four elbows together one
two
three
four
next we go to
the back
one
two
three
four
then we go overhead
one
um two
three
four oh wow
and
then come straight forward
one
two
three
four
and then comes
some people think it's the hardest
the shoulder blade kiss
shoulder blade kiss or
diagonal
okay we've got diagonally forward and
back as far as we can so as to make our
shoulder blades
kiss each other they can't but we tried
and one
two
three
four
now you can tell I haven't been doing
these
because I'm out of breath
doing just four instead of eight of each
of these
and then we end again with back and
front one two
three
four
five
six
seven
eight
all right I'm leaving it there for today
[Music]
and when I do more
um arm
we will also include push-ups
and I don't do push-ups from the floor I
do but they're so tiny
that it's better to show you to go from
a bench or even
counter top or table one
two
three
four
and now you will say some will say
that's not low enough you know the push
but it's okay we go even if it's just a
tiny little Bend in your elbows it will
strengthen your arms very considerably
and your shoulders and this muscle
tissues in the front of your shoulders
all right
I'm going to quickly show you the chair
exercises
um
and then we have to
round it out otherwise this is going to
be an hour long introduction
okay we sit at the very very edge
sideways on the chair it does not work
if you sit regular on the chair all
right
and you hold them to the back of the
chair and onto the seat and you tilt
back and lift up your feet
and you kick those legs out
one two three four kick your heels one
two three four then we tilt one two
three four other side tilt two three
four and Center two three four but of
course also on the count of eight
and if that is too hard for you to begin
then your exercise is going to be this
one
two
three
four and then heels and try and keep
your back straight
not all the way straight but
don't crunch your organs that's the main
thing then we kick the heels
two
three four so you go through the routine
like this as opposed to all up in the
air
and
we then typically
walk around the chair
just to get our legs
moving differently
sit at the other side
and kick up both legs together one
two
three four like that and then heels
again at everything else
and for those who are beginners you can
try
that
it's still going to be hard for you
trust me
um
if you can't do both legs together
continue one leg at a time
it will begin to strengthen your legs so
that you get to
tilting up and kicking in the air
all right there's more to the routines
up in the air there's all kinds of fun
stuff like the kikaroo we do sometimes
where we make loud noises and kick until
we can't
anymore we laugh at ourselves and it's a
wonderful thing to um
encourage endurance with fun
and
it's a miraculous thing it always works
so
then we have
the last chair exercise is
belly crunches and there we either leave
our feet for the beginners we leave our
feet on the floor again and we just move
the upper body up and down and it's
perfectly fine to start
with
Holding On And even pulling yourself up
a little
you will soon be able to
do it
like this
on like this whichever way works okay
but we have a all body version of that
that I prefer where again we're sitting
at the edge
legs are up and over cross and the
entire body goes out and in up and in
out
oh
all right again on the count of eight
with a tilt on four and another tilt on
four and
coming back
that is of course abdominal work and if
we do the all body like I told you in
the introduction
I try to always involve the entire body
in every exercise even though the
emphasis is
in the chair exercises is on belly
um
now there are other exercises
that we will do in the when we emphasize
the waste
[Music]
all right
then
for both sides and forget up
we will do full squats
um now many of us cannot get up with our
arms in the air
so we do this
and that includes me
I start with a swing to straighten the
back and one
two
three
four now I put my arms forward and we go
down
all the way
to crouching position now if you can't
get back up like me I cannot get back up
without touching the ground you touch
the ground in front of you push it a
little and then get the rest
on your leg power
the count doesn't matter because it's
not a rhythmical
thing
and then do something else and then
maybe another 10
and of course that goes into your thighs
all right and quickly
a couple of bits or sizes
one is half squats
half squats
um can also be with your arms forward
they can also be just tiny like this
for your beginners
they will always if you come back
to straightening your knees and putting
your shoulders back and your butt tight
they will
strengthen
your glutes
um and of course size and everything
else as well
and then there's a series of butter
sizes that are actually on the floor and
go
to the back
to the side
and or just the knee to the side or the
knee up in the back
and or the straight leg up in the back
and again
we operate on the count of eight
and
we know that
we can
strengthen our muscle tissue
significantly
like that
and while
I sound all out of breath right now
because I'm trying to put a little bit
of everything in here
finally there are things like get UPS
so I choose
a little stool now I'm tall I'm five
nine
so for me
this is hard to get up from a low stool
for some of you it may just be a brick
kind of height
you know when you're not tall
empty
the emphasis here is on getting up again
without touching anything and I had to
literally train myself to bounce my back
back and forth to be able to get up from
this little stool
and now I can every time but I could not
I could not get up from this very stool
five years ago even three years ago has
happened in this house and I've only
been in this house for two years so
that is to tell you that you can
gain strength at any age
and
get your physical
control over your body back
so
get UPS involve these kind of exercises
and of course
they do need repetition and a lot of
repetition so that the strengthening
um happens in the repetition you know
you go down you go back up you go down
you go back up
and the muscles
have to do this rhythmical repetition
enough times to really
require the body to build that tissue
otherwise it's just an odd situation out
that doesn't do anything like you know
okay today I had to climb five stairs
you know but it's once in a lifetime or
you know it doesn't kind of do diddly to
your muscle tissue
other than you feeling it the next day
like oh my God that was so hard those
five stairs
all right
um
I'm sure I've forgotten some important
stuff like Plies Behind the Chair and
there's other things that I do in
between that create variations
and of course I didn't show you the
strength exercises and the breathing and
so much more so but because I have this
routine of starting and finishing with
my little ritual I will do it again
reach two three four five six seven
eight swing
two
three
four
five
six
seven
eight I love you my planet
I love you my sunshine
I love you Humanity
I love you my body
and it's important that you do say those
words even if you feel embarrassed and
you don't want to say them out loud you
say them in your
head because it literally changes the
chemistry of your relationship with the
planet with the sunshine with humanity
and with your own body
you know as quantum physics advance and
as we get more into understanding that
behind all matter is energy
holding atoms together holding molecules
together holding
structures in place such as all bodies
whether it's the body of a tree or the
body of a human
since we understand more and more that
we the human mind
the human being
actually can to a certain extent that
biology allows biology is not endlessly
variable
we can influence our biological
well-being we can influence the
production of certain hormones like
endorphins and serotonin and
we can influence our bodies healing
ability
Etc so
I'm not saying we can change into a
horse
biology is biology it's limited
so
we however can enhance this body that we
have
substantially and have therefore a
happier more fulfilled more functional
life with those muscles in place that we
need to remain upright happy and
productive
because only when we're meaningfully
productive do we feel accomplished and
do we have such as feelings such a thing
as satisfaction and that is a form of
happiness
all right guys this has been your
introduction into fitness over 50 and in
the next class we're going to do the
full routine with an emphasis on arm
muscle tissue
ciao this has been Professor Johanna
Sophia of johanna's raw foods and
coaching the rasamlife global.com
um online college
that is in development
and you can get all kinds of information
on my YouTube channel so subscribe to my
YouTube channel Johannes raw foods
follow me on I'm not on Twitter
I mean I am but I don't do anything
there so but you can see me on all other
social media whether it's Facebook or
Instagram or Tick Tock I do quite a bit
on Tick Tock and I'm on LinkedIn of
course and again you know subscribe to
the YouTube channel where there is quite
a bit of material as well for free
[Music]
um at the time
and then you can get more personalized
help if you want I I cannot even tell
you what a difference it made that I
hired a personal trainer last summer for
a whole bunch of months that
encouraged me to go beyond what I
already was able to do and that is just
a wonderful gift you can give yourself
allow a coach to personalize your
particular training or your particular
desire to become healthier happier more
fit and more functional so you can hire
me for those purposes
but you have to step into action
you know where to find me you can just
Google me and and
um Professor Johanna Sophia will always
get you all kinds of information on how
to make contact so that I can
help
ciao for now